all right
[Music]
according to the American Dental
Association about 50 percent of American
adults suffer from oral Mal odor with
prevalence rates around the world
ranging from two percent to nearly 80
percent on average it seems to be about
one in three of us on the planet Earth
have bad breath what effect might stress
have on the smell of our breath stress
students were found to have
significantly higher levels of the
rotten egg gas hydrogen sulfide which is
one of the main volatile silver
compounds related to bad breath
originated from the degradation of the
sulfur-containing amino acid cysteine
found concentrated in animal proteins
like meat and dairy were they eating
different diets or just too busy to
brush the simplest explanation is just
the dry mouth you get when you're super
stressed part of our fight-or-flight
response it's the same reason we get
morning breath because we have decreased
saliva production when we sleep that
would otherwise self-clean the mouth
keeping it from becoming like a stagnant
Palm Bond though maybe stress hormones
are having an effect as well
we suspect sex hormones may play a role
since though men and women have the same
before and after rise in bad breath
compounds after a stressful situation
women seem to start out with higher
Baseline levels gender appears to play
an important role women have
significantly worse morning breath for
example and bad breath is affected by
the menstrual cycle in fact that's
listed as one of the causes so-called
menstrual breath as you can see there
are higher levels of bad breath
compounds in the mouths of women in the
premenstrual and menstrual phases
compared not just to men but the
follicular phase of their own cycle
meaning like the first half before
ovulation so maybe bad breath is a
hormonal thing more than just a dry
mouth thing but salivary flow is also
lower in menstrual and premenstrual
phases check it out significantly less
salivary flow during menstrual flow and
right before so is this all just about
having a dryer mouth during stress in
certain times of the month how could you
tease out the effects
well what about studying stressful
periods
PMS premenstrual syndrome is a stressful
State characterized by irritability
tension mood swings is the menstrual dry
mouth and bad breath just due to period
stress
apparently so if you split women up into
those who experience PMs and those who
don't it's only those with PMS who
suffer the rise in bad breath compounds
as their period arrives but the salivary
flow was not statistically different so
the result suggests that a stressful
situation can be a predisposing factor
for bad breath that may have nothing to
do with dry mouth or salivary flow so
what's going on
the effects of the stress hormones
themselves on the production of bad
breath compounds they drip some stress
hormones on bad breath bacteria hormones
like adrenaline and cortisol and they
started churning out more hydrogen
sulfide
what can we do about it if we can't
treat the cause and reduce the stress I
have videos on dietary changes that can
help as well as tongue cleaning methods
and I have videos in the works on the
effects of gum chewing and the best
mouthwash to use that doesn't kill the
good bacteria in your mouth stay tuned
foreign